MICHELE CLAIBOURN

I am a research director - a political scientist, data scientist, community-engaged scholar, and senior administrator - and professor with 20 years of experience teaching, leading, and managing research and data science teams.

My work centers on action-based research, using the tools of data science to promote accountable governance, make social inequities visible, and impact public policy and movement building.



PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2022 2021

Director of Equitable Analysis, Asst Professor of Public Policy

The Equity Center and The Batten School of Leadership and Public Policy, University of Virginia

- · Leading the Democratization of Data initiative in the UVA Equity Center to provide data tools, research and analysis in collaboration with leaders and advocates promoting regional equity.
- · Teaching courses on data ethics and practice, visualization, and equitable policy in the Batten School of Leadership and Public Policy.
- · Faculty Affiliate & Lead Data Scientist, Global Policy Center (2019-2021), using predictive analytics on the timing, magnitude, and duration of massdisplacement in partnership with Save the Children, International.

2021 2013

Director, Research Data Services & Sciences

UVA Library, University of Virginia

- · Built a new research data services team to support data use and infrastructure, managed and developed library staff and services for the social, natural, and engineering sciences, and provided statistical and data science consultation and instruction to researchers across disciplines including on the collection, analysis, and interpretation of data.
- Data Science Director, The Equity Center, 2020-2021 (partial buyout)
- · Associate Director, Data Science Institute, 2014-2016 (partial buyout)

2013 2011

Data Scientist

Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, University of Virginia

· Design and conduct quantiative research for local governments, civic sector clients, and the public interest.

2011 2002

Assistant Professor

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

- · Department of Politics. University of Virginia (2004-2011): Department of Political Science, University of Oklahoma (2002-2004).
- · Desiged and taught graduate-level research and statistics courses and undergraduate-level courses on political behavior and political psychology.
- · Developed, implemented, and published new research on social capital, electoral responsiveness, and political communication from ideation, data collection and wrangling, analysis and communication.



EDUCATION

2002 1996

1989

PhD., Political Science

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, WI

1993

B.A. Political Science

Rice University

OHouston, TX

CONTACT

mclaibourn.github.io

github.com/mclaibourn

in linkedin.com/in/mclaibourn

Project portfolio at mclaibourn.github.io.

Leadership

Envision, design, and lead research projects with academic and community partners seeking to understand racial and other disparities and to develop policy responses. Manage multiple projects and train and mentor students engaging in communityengaged data science.

Founded StatLab, a data science consulting service for members of the UVA community. Built a new division within the library to support the growing data science research community at UVA, recruiting, hiring, and managing a team with diverse skills and talents.

Managed a team of 10-12 full-time staff, 3-4 graduate fellows, and research teams across mulitple collaborations on a range of programmatic and research projects.

♣■ TEACHING AND MENTORING

2022 | 2002

Graduate Courses

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

· Imagining Equitable Policy, Public Interest Data: Ethics & Practice, Data Visualization, Saving Lives with Data, Text as Data, Applied Causal Inference, General Linear Models, Linear Models, Applied Time Series, Mixed-Effects Models/Longitudinal Analysis, Introduction to Statistical Analysis

2021 | 2013

University-wide Workshops

University of Virginia

 Data Science in R, Multiple Imputation, Cluster Analysis, Duration Models, Matching Methods, Mixed-Effects Models, Sentiment Analysis, Topic Modeling, Text Classification, Data Wrangling, Linear Modeling

2020 | 2002

2007

Undergraduate Courses

University of Virginia and University of Oklahoma

 Project First Gen +, Research Design & Analysis, The Presidency and the Public, Media & Political Communication, Political Pscyology & Decision Making, Citizen Competence in American Democracy, Introduction to American Politics



SELECTED PUBLICATIONS AND PROJECTS

Confederate monuments and the history of lynching in the American South:
An empirical examination

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Oct 2021 (With Kyshia Henderson, Samuel Powers, Jazmin L. Brown-lannuzzi, and Sophie Trawalter)

Citizen Participation and Congressional Responsiveness: New Evidence for Why Participation Matters

Legislative Studies Quarterly 38: 59-82 (With Paul Martin)

2012 • Creating Constituencies: Presidential Campaigns, Selective Mobilization, and the Scope of Conflict

Political Behavior 34: 27-56 (With Paul Martin)

2011 • Presidential Campaigns and Presidential Accountability²

University of Illinois Press, Series on Democracy, Free Enterprise, and the Rule of Law

• The Third Face of Social Capital: How membership in Voluntary Associations Improves Policy Accountability

Political Research Quarterly 60: 192-201 (With Paul Martin)

Trusting and Joining: An Empirical Test of the Reciprocal Nature of Social Capital

Political Behavior 22: 267-291 (With Paul Martin)

2022 • Virgina Evictors Catalog³

The Equity Center, University of Virginia and The RVA Eviction Lab, Virginia Commonwealth University (With Kate Howell, Jacob Goldstein-Greenwood, Elizabeth Mitchell, Ben Teresa, Connor White, Barbara Brown Wilson, and Hannah Woerhle)

Teaching and Writing

20+ years of experience teaching statistics and data science methods, policy, and political behavior to undergraduate and graduate students.

Design data workshop series for student and adult learning communities, including recruiting and mentoring instructors, marketing and assessment, and contributing to select topics.

Experienced writer in multiple formats, from university press books and peer-reviewed journal articles, to action-oriented reports for local and state agencies, educational materials, and informal writing.

Skilled in communicating about data, technology, and policy to stakeholders, advocates, and learners.

Methods and Software

Inferential and predictive modeling
Data visualization and computation
Text analytics
R, RStudio, Shiny
GitHub and reproducibility
Stata and SPSS
Some Python and SQL
Qualitative methods

Last updated on 2023-01-03.

2022		Orange Dot Report 5.0: Family Self-Sufficiency in the Charlottesville Region ⁴ Network2Work@PVCC, Piedmont Virginia Community College and The Equity Center, University of Virginia (With Ridge Schuyler, Lee LeBoeuf, and Beth Mitchell)
2022	•	Charlottesville Region Climate Equity Atlas ⁵ Picturing Climate Justice Exhibit, UVA Equity Center and the Jefferson
		School African American Heritage Center
2021		Albemarle County Equity Profile: Centering Equity in Evaluating Well-Being & Quality of LIfe for Albemarle County Residents ⁶
		The Equity Center, University of Virginia (With Sam Powers, Michael Salgueiro, Siri Russell, Barbara Brown Wilson, and Alissa Ujie Diamond)
2020	•	Child Welfare Referrals in Charlottesville
		Report to the Charlottesville Department of Social Services (With Hannah Lewis and the Public Interest Data Lab)